Venkat Suprabath Bitra

Columbia University in the City of New York, New York, USA

८ +91 62642 79074 **▼** <u>vsb2127@columbia.edu</u> **in** linkedin.com/in/venkat-suprabath **⊘** github.com/VenkatSBitra

Objective

My interest lies in Computer Vision, Multimodal Machine Learning and its applications. I have experience in Computer Vision and Reinforcement Learning. My ambition is to plan my career to develop fail-safe ML-based systems for real-life applications.

Education

Columbia University, USA

Starting Sep 2024

Masters of Science in Computer Science

IIIT Bangalore, India

Aug 2019 - Jul 2024

Integrated Masters of Technology in Computer Science and Engineering

3.85 / 4

Experience

International Institute of Information Technology Bangalore

Jan 2024 – Jun 2024

Master's Thesis Project

Bangalore, India

- Optimized Moving Object Segmentation using an existing model on Two RGB frames and geometric properties of image formation.
- Detailed case studies on different cost maps of the model and identifying the limiting cases and improved the model performance through cost correction as a post-processing step.
- Integrated Panoptic Segmentation along with Optical flow to improve semantic awareness to further improve accuracy of the model.

Statistics and Machine Learning Laboratory, UBC Okanagan Campus [7]

 $\mathbf{Aug}\ \mathbf{2023} - \mathbf{Dec}\ \mathbf{2023}$

Research Intern

Kelowna, Canada

- Performed statistical analysis for unsupervised classification of radiochromic film data for different radiation doses of biomedical samples.
- Identification of a loss function to improve performance of 1D CNN model for data pre-processing of spectroscopic data for biomedical applications.

Adobe Research

May 2023 - Jul 2023

Research Intern

Bangalore, India

- Create visually cohesive branded images/designs of a product based on brand references and guidelines.
- Worked on diffusion models and incorporated multimodal constraints in form of text and visual inputs to enhance controlled image generation streamlining design creation.

Multimodal Perception Lab, IIITB

Jan 2023 – May 2023

Research Intern

Bangalore, India

- Implemented a novel UV texture map based design for generation and semantic manipulation of virtual human heads in 3D space using GANs.
- Demonstrated strong identity preservation during semantic manipulation of features such as age, gender, and facial hair in different 3D orientations.
- Provided approach is simple and agnostic to 3D components such as lighting and rendering, enabling seamless integration into standard 3D graphics pipelines.

Laser Materials Processing Division, RRCAT

Dec 2022 - Jan 2023

 $Research\ Intern$

Indore, India

- Demonstrated a novel application of TinyML for realization of next-generation offline on-device ML computation for Raman spectrometers.
- Implemented various ML/DL models like PCA-SVM/kNN/LR, CNN, DNN etc. for smartphones to perform Raman spectra analysis for on-site applications.
- Developed Android app for controlling Arduino Mega based linear four axis CNC workstation for different human-free laboratory experiments.

May 2022 - Dec 2022

Research Intern

Bangalore, India

- Studied GAN based models for style transfer and lip synchronization in audio-video generation.
- Implemented different style transfer and lip synchronization GAN models as reported in the literature and performed testing and comparison on custom datasets.
- Implemented of Computer Graphics integrated GAN models towards quality improvement in semantic manipulation of human faces.

Laser Materials Processing Division, RRCAT

Dec 2021 - Jan 2022

Research Intern

Indore, India

- Developed an automated vision based real-time monitoring and Arduino driven control of solvents for a novel chemical process to obtain large area gold nanoparticle films for various applications.
- Performed detailed principal component analysis based ML classification of closely related spectra/signals with various data pre-processing methods.
- Developed a WebApp for automatic processing of multiple UV-Visible spectra to determine kinetics of chemical reactions.

Graphics Visualization Computing Lab, IIITB

May 2021 – Jul 2021

Research Intern

Bangalore, India

- Designed programs in R language for preparation of genomic data (DNA methylation features and mRNA genes) for different cancer phenotypes provided in The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) open data repository.
- Extracted significant subspaces from the large-scale genomic feature space for a novel data visualization.
- Incorporated features for RadTrix data visualization tool to show the correlations in the reduced gene space.

Web Science Laboratory, IIITB

Apr 2020 - Jun 2020

Research Intern

Bangalore, India

• Developed an interactive simulator using React, ReCharts, Python and Flask that implements an extended SEIR model for estimating epidemic spread and incorporated data of COVID-19 to simulate its spread in various regions.

Projects

Reinforcement Learning based Chatbot | Python, PyTorch, TensorFlow

Jan - May 2023

- Design two chatbots (Agent A and Agent B) using policy gradient based training strategies so that they can handle natural conversations between them
- Design and implement additional strategies that can further prolong meaningful conversations between Agent A and Agent B.
- Implement training techniques to give two separate personas for Agent A and Agent B.

Abacus based Mental Calculation using Neuromorphic Architecture | Python, Nengo

Aug - Dec 2022

• Implementation of different abacus based arithmetic operations to mimic mental calculations using Neural Engineering Framework.

Oceanic Data Visualization (Data Visualization Course Project) | Python, Svelte, Flask, D3.js

Aug 2022

 Designed a web application to visualize various features of Indian Ocean and Arabian Sea during the period of 29 Dec 2003 to 29 Dec 2005.

2048 Playing Agent (Personal Project) | Python, PyTorch, Jupyter

Jun 2022

• Designed a reinforcement learning agent to play 2048 using different algorithms DQN, PPO, NEAT and Markov Trees.

Visual Programming Language (Programming Languages Course Project) | JavaScript, Blockly

Jan 2022

• Web based visual programming language to emulate Turtle using Blockly transpiler for equivalent JS code generation.

Image Captioning Tool (Visual Recognition Course Project) | Python, TensorFlow, Jupyter

May 2022

• A CNN-LSTM network was implemented using InceptionNetv3 as feature extractor to label various images provided in the publically available Flickr8K dataset.

Comprehensive Spectroscopic Data Processing and Visualization Tool | Python, React, ECharts Mar - May 2022

- Designed a full-stack novel software tool for comprehensive data analysis of batch Raman spectra with features like background correction, peaks analysis, heatmaps, SNV, PCA-SVM analysis, spectral data libraries etc.
- Utilised React and Apache ECharts for designing frontend and data visualizations of the analysed data provided by backend built using Python and Flask.
- Embedded various machine learning models using Python and scikit-learn for determination of compounds for applications like identifying pesticides.

Auto Rickshaw Detection (Visual Recognition Course Project) | Python, PyTorch, Jupyter

Mar 2022

• Designed object detection model using YOLOv5 on self curated and labelled set of images of auto rickshaw.

Web Scraping Tool (Personal Project) | Python, Selenium, SQLite

Jan 2022

• Program to scrape publication DOI and other details from different publisher websites based on user given keywords and record them in a database for ease of querying for researchers.

NLP based Sentiment Analysis (Machine Learning Course Project) | Python, Scikit-Learn, Jupyter

Dec 2021

• Machine Learning model for multiclass classification of a sentence into six different types of sentimentally hurting classes; hosted as Community Kaggle Competition.

Face Recognition based Security System (Hackathon Project) | PyTorch, Scikit-Learn, OpenCV

Jan 2020

• Real time image pre-processing and face detection using OpenCV and Python integrated with pretrained Deep Learning model to determine strangers and owners.

Publications

SemUV: Deep Learning based semantic manipulation over UV texture map of virtual human heads Dec 2024 Anirban Mukherjee, Venkat Suprabath Bitra, Vignesh Bondugula, Tarun Reddy Tallapureddy, Dinesh Babu Jayagopi 9th International Conference on Computer Vision & Image Processing (CVIP 2024)

Optical response of Au films for reproducible Si nano-structuring and its application for efficient Sep 2023 micro-drop SERS with portable Raman system

Shweta Verma, Venkat Suprabath Bitra, R. Singh, B. Tirumala Rao

Materials Chemistry and Physics, Volume 306, 2023, 128058, ISSN 0254-0584

Machine Learning and Convolutional Neural Network based Trace Identification of Pesticides and Jan 2023

Dye Mixtures from Raman Spectra

Venkat Suprabath Bitra, Shweta Verma, B. Tirumala Rao

 6^{th} Joint International Conference on Data Science & Management of Data (CODS-COMAD 2023) \square

Software for Comprehensive Batch Analysis of Raman/SERS Spectra with Real-time Interactive Dec 2022 Visualization and Machine Learning Predictions

Venkat Suprabath Bitra

IX International Conference on Perspectives in Vibrational Spectroscopy (ICOPVS-2022)

Indigenous development of automated cost-effective system for SERS measurements with data anal- Dec 2022 ysis and compound prediction

Shweta Verma, Venkat Suprabath Bitra, B. Tirumala Rao

IX International Conference on Perspectives in Vibrational Spectroscopy (ICOPVS-2022)

An Interactive Simulator for COVID-19 Trend Analysis

Programming in C++ and Java (ESS 201)

Jan 2021

Aug 2021 - Dec 2021

IIIT Bangalore

Jayati Deshmukh, Raksha Pavagada Subbanarasimha, Pooja Bassin, **Venkat Suprabath Bitra**, Srinath Srinivasa, and Anupama Sharma

3th Joint International Conference on Data Science & Management of Data (CODS-COMAD 2021)

Mentorship

Teaching Assistant

<u>-</u>	
Linear Algebra (SM 102) Teaching Assistant	Jan 2024 – May 2024 IIIT Bangalore
Digital Design (ESS 102) Teaching Assistant	Aug 2023 – Dec 2023 IIIT Bangalore
Visual Recognition (AI 825) Teaching Assistant	Jan 2023 – May 2023 IIIT Bangalore
Introduction to Machine Learning (AI 511) Teaching Assistant	Aug 2022 – Dec 2022 IIIT Bangalore

Technical Skills

Languages: Python, Java, C, C++, Dart, JavaScript, TyeScript, R, SQL, Verilog, HTML, CSS, MATLAB Technologies/Frameworks: Nengo, Linux, Git, GitHub, Arduino, Arduino Nano Sense, Raspberry Pi, PyTorch, TensorFlow, Svelte, ReactJS, Redux, Android, NextJS, NodeJS, ExpressJS, D3.js, Jenkins, MongoDB, Flutter, Blockly, LaTeX

Relevant Coursework

Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning: Machine Learning, Math for Machine Learning, Visual Recognition, Reinforcement Learning, Few-shot Learning, Causal Inference and Learning, Neuromorphic Computing Computer Science: Topics in Computability and Learning, Data Visualization, Software Testing, Operating Systems, Programming Languages, Software Engineering, Introduction to Automata Theory and Computability, Database Systems, Object Oriented Programming, Design and Analysis of Algorithms, Data Structures and Algorithms, Programming Electronics and Communication: Signals and Systems, Computer Architecture, Digital Design, Computer Networks Mathematics and Basic Sciences: Graph Theory, Probability, Statistics, Linear Algebra, Calculus, Real Analysis, Physics, Chemistry

Social Sciences: Software Product Management, Social Complexity and Systems Thinking, History of Ideas, Technical Communication, Economics, English

Achievements

- Graduate Aptitude Test in Engineering (GATE) 2023; All India Rank: 271 GATE Score: 742
- Deans Merit List Year 2019-20, IIITB
- Deans Merit List Year 2020-21, IIITB
- Deans Merit List Year 2021-22, IIITB
- Deans Merit List Year 2022-23, IIITB
- Merit Based Scholarship 2020-21, IIITB
- Merit Based Scholarship 2021-22, IIITB
- Second Prize by Cartesi in ETHIndia 2022 Hackathon
- Second Prize in Team Hackathon Inclusive Stem Confluence 2020

Certifications

- Machine Learning Verzeo (2020)
- NVIDIA DLI: Fundamentals of Deep Learning (2021)
- NVIDIA DLI: Building Transformer-Based Natural Language Processing Applications (2021) ☑
- Crash Course on Python (by Google, Coursera)
- Mathematics for Machine Learning: Linear Algebra (by Imperial College London, Coursera)
- Problem Solving (Basic) by HackerRank
- Java (Basic) by HackerRank